Mss.B.T63.1 Mss.B.T63.1
American Philosophical Society
John Torrey papers, 1819-1864
Mss.B.T63.1
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
These papers include letters on natural history, metals and mineralogy, botany, insects, the geological survey of New York, and analyses of distilled liquors in the cause of temperance.
15 items.
Torrey, John, 1796-1873
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1958 (1958 160ms). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
John Torrey was a botanist, and was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1835.
Naval History Note
The Torrey Papers contain at least two items which may be of interest to naval historians:
Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877.
Torrey, John. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1848 January. Is afraid his work will suffer since the committee refused his request for aid. 2 pages.
Torrey, John. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1848 January 28. Concerning plants which he received from Charles Wilkes. 1 page.
Early American History Note
The John Torrey Papers consist of two separate collections. The first contains original documents, often from John Torrey, a prominent botanist in the nineteenth century. Torrey’s letters often discuss natural history, books, and flora. Amos Eaton is his most regular correspondent, and the letters are often of a personal nature in which Torrey gives Eaton support for his scientific pursuits. Mention is also made of temperance. This portion of the collection is relatively small. The second part of the collection contains various notes and transcriptions Chapman Robbins made for a study she undertook on Torrey. This larger part of the collection consists of over two boxes of transcriptions of Torrey correspondence and provides a far more complete picture of Torrey.
Buckley, S. B., (Samuel Botsford), 1809-1884; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858; Delavan, Edward C., (Edward Cornelius), 1793-1871; Durand, Elie M.; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842; Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877; Botany.; Geology -- New York (State) -- Surveys.; Insects.; Mineralogy.; Natural History; Natural history.; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Temperance.
- Papers
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Northampton, Mass., Nov. 1, 1817; 7-3/4x6; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    Scope and Contents note
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning a work on botany. Refers to LeConte's collection,and comments on Mitchill, and the Pursh collection.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Albany, March 12, 1819; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L. 3p., add. Comments on geological and botanical matters; particularly on grasses. Mentions Gibbs, Silliman, Cleaveland, Pomeroy, Pursh, Nuttall and Mühlenberg.
  - Letter to Dennis Cooley, Muddy-brook, Mass., May 4, 1819; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.add.end. Concerning collection/exchange of plants/minerals. Lyceum of Natural History of N.Y. pub. Torrey's "Catalogue... Asks for grasses, mosses,ferns. Mentions Dr. Ives,Mr. Hitchcock.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Troy, May 18, 1819; 10x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning botanical matters. Concerning Rafinesque. Refers to Nuttall.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Troy, Dec. 11, 1819; 10-1/2x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Mineralogy and botany of the U.S. Concerning the preservation of insects. Refers to Nuttall and Rafinesque.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Troy, New York, March 7, 1820; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.add & end. Concerns geology and botany; esp. mosses & grasses. Critical of Akerly's book on Geology. Mentions Gibbs, Hosack, James, McClure, Mitchell, Muhlengerg, Paulding, & Pierce.
  - Letter to Parker Cle[a]veland, Bowdoin college, Dec. 28, 1820; 10x7-1/2; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Mineralogical sources in the U.S. Refers to Jacob Bigelow.
  - Letter to Parker Cleaveland, Brunswick, Jan. 11, 1827; 9-1/2x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    West Point, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning mineralogy. Refers to Nuttall.
  - Letter to ----, April 10, 1828; 7-3/4x4-3/4; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see John Torrey papers.) Forwards package of pamphlets. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to T. A. Greene, New Bedford, Mass, Sept. 10, 1831; 10x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning botanical specimens of the U.S. Orders certain items.
  - Letter to Professor A[mos] Eaton, Oct. 29, 1831; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, ... fungi published by A.P.S. 1. Botany--Kentucky. 2. Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842. 3. Le Conte, John Lawrence, 1825-1883. 4. Lindley, John, 1779-1865. 5. Rafinesque- Schmaltz, Constantine Samuel, 1783-1840. 6. Schweinitz, Lewis David von, 1780-1834.
  - Letter to E[lie Magliore] Durand, Philadelphia, Feb. 1, 1834; 10x7-3/4; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning certain botanical specimens which they have studied. Refers to Nuttall.
  - Letter to E[dward] C. Delavan, Albany, Feb. 19, 1834; 10x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning his analysis of whiskeys for the temperance cause.
  - Letter to Prof. Henry, June, 1836; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    Photo of A.L.S. 1p. and add. From original in University of Amsterdam Library.
    Item previously cataloged as: B T63.2
  - John Torrey to John Vaughan, July 3, 1838; 8" x 10"; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, 1 p. and address. A.L.S. Introducing Mr. H. J. Jones Brydges, of England, "an interesting scientific traveller." At work with Dr. [Asa] Gray upon The Flora of North America.
  - Letter to W. W. Treadway, Albany, April 4, 1840; 10x7-1/2; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see John Torrey papers.) Forwards his account for serving as botanist in the geological survey.
  - Letter to J. W. Bailey, West Point, April 6, 1840; 10x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 4p.,add. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning natural history and how it should be written up. Refers to Henry and Gray. Concerning certain laboratory experiments on metals.
  - Letter to Jo[h]n K[irk] Townsend, Philadelphia, Feb. 2, 1841; 10x8; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning a possible subscriber to the expedition. Refers to Nuttall.
  - Letter to S[amuel] B. Buckley, Allentown, Ala., March 10, 1841; 10x7-3/4; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning botanical matters of the U.S Concerning his forthcoming publication.
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 28, 1848; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see John Torrey papers.) Concerning plants which he received from Charles Wilkes.
  - Letter to Ch[arles] Wilkes, Jan., 1848; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. (see John Torrey papers.) Is afraid his work will suffer since the committee refused his request for aid.
  - Letter to ----, Oct. 15, 1864; 8x5; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see John Torrey papers.) General news. Refers to Henry.